Finding Aid for Bela Hubbard papers, 1837-1893
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bela Hubbard papers 1837-1893
Hubbard, Bela, 1814-1896.
1 oversize folders
0.75 linear feet (in 2 boxes)
851637 Ac Aa 2
Pioneer Michigan geologist, assistant to state geologist Douglas Houghton on the Michigan Geological Survey, 1837-1842, completed portions of U.S. Land Survey of the Upper Peninsula begun by Douglas Houghton, 1845-1846. Later active in family's land business and lumber trade. Papers consist of notebooks containing field notes, sketches and maps; private journals covering Michigan geological expeditions and other trips, including the peninsula coast survey, Lake Superior and Upper Peninsula surveys and surveys of Wayne, Monroe and other counties; also weather memoranda, 1835-1864; miscellaneous accounts; and other papers largely relating to geology.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came to the library in two accessions. In 1947, Josephine Sherzer (donor 2331 ), the daughter of Eastern Michigan University geologist William H. Sherzer, donated Hubbard's notebooks for 1838 and 1873-1884 and two notebooks of weather observations. It is unclear how these notebooks came into the possession of the Sherzer family. In 1958, Helen M. Martin (donor 3485 ), research geologist for the Michigan Geological Survey, donated Hubbard's notebooks for 1837-1852 and other material. These papers had been given to the Geological Survey, apparently in the 1920s, by a grandson of Hubbard, also named Bela Hubbard.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Notebooks in Vols. 7, 8, 10-12 (in part), 21, and 22, have been microfilmed. Master negative only.
Bela Hubbard is noted as one of the pioneer geologists of Michigan as a result of expeditions undertaken, while in his twenties, with Douglass Houghton, Sylvester Higgins, and William Ives. For the rest of his long life, he occupied himself as a Detroit land speculator and lumber dealer.
Hubbard was born in Hamilton, New York, in 1814, but moved as a child to Utica, New York. In 1834 he graduated from Hamilton College, and soon thereafter moved to Detroit to join his brother Henry in managing the family's farm and land agency. Hubbard was active in the Detroit Young Men's Society, serving as corresponding secretary and, in 1845, as president.
In 1837, shortly after the Michigan Legislature established a geological survey to conduct a comprehensive study of the state's natural resources, the new state geologist, Douglass Houghton, appointed Hubbard his assistant. Hubbard served the Geological Survey from 1837 to 1841. Major field work undertaken by Hubbard for the survey included a coast survey of the Lake Huron and Michigan shores of the Lower Peninsula, done with Houghton in 1838; surveys of Wayne and Monroe Counties, also in 1838; and a survey of the Lake Superior coast and the copper region of Keweenaw Point with Houghton, in 1840. After 1840 the work of the Geological Survey was reduced, and Hubbard left the agency.
Hubbard returned to Detroit in 1841 to study law. He began writing a column in the Western Farmer, becoming the editor in 1842. The journal ceased publication in 1843.
In 1843 Houghton proposed that the U.S. land survey of the Upper Peninsula be combined with the state geological survey of the area. The following summer he contracted to perform the combined surveys. After Houghton's death in the fall of 1845, the surveys he had contracted to do were taken over by Hubbard and others. Hubbard surveyed the Huron Mountains area of Marquette and Baraga Counties with William Ives in 1845 and 1846. He also surveyed parts of Houghton and Ontonagon Counties in those years with Sylvester Higgins. Also in 1846 Hubbard edited and published with William Burt a report on the copper region based on Houghton's notes from his 1845 survey.
After 1846 Hubbard left the field of geological survey, concerning himself more with the family land business. In 1854 he entered the lumber trade. Hubbard died in 1896, and is buried in Elmwood Cemetery, Detroit.
The collection consists primarily of Hubbard's pocket-size field notebooks. The notebooks are arranged, for the most part, chronologically for the period 1837 to 1893. Several notebooks that do not fit the chronological sequence are placed at the end of the series of notebooks. The notebooks for the years 1837 to 1840 have been bound, probably by Hubbard, into larger volumes. For convenience the later notebooks have been grouped into "volumes" by the library. Each "volume" is in a separate case. The notebooks contain personal journals, geological notes, and meteorological registers, along with sketches of landforms, scenery, and people, geological sections, and maps.
A few loose papers are found at the end of the collection.
The most extensive notebooks are those written between 1837 and 1840, when Hubbard was working for the Michigan Geological Survey, and in 1845 and 1846, when he was conducting the combined land and geological survey of the Upper Peninsula. In addition to the main sequence of notebooks for those years (volumes 1-8 and 10-12), that period is represented by separate meteorological registers (volumes 18 and 22), separate geological field notes for the 1840 expedition to the Lake Superior region (volume 21), and three reports on Hubbard's 1846 surveys (volumes 23-24 and loose papers).
This finding aid contains two appendixes. The first, compiled by the initial cataloger of the collection in 1958, specifies where many of the topics indexed in the card catalog for this collection can be found in the series of notebooks. The second contains an inventory of the maps found in the collection.
Several portions of the collection have been published.
The notebooks for May 23-August 8, 1840 (volumes 7-9 and parts of 21) have been published as
Lake Superior Journal: Bela Hubbard's Account of the 1840 Houghton Expedition}, edited by Bernard C. Peters. Marquette, Mich.: Northern Michigan University Press, 1983. [MHC call number EA/91/H875/L192]
The "Catalogue of the Geological Specimens, Hubbard & Ives Survey, 1846" (volume 23), the "Report on the Geology &c. of District Surveyed by Messrs. Higgins & Hubbard, 1846, Lake Superior, with Catalogue of Minerals, Sections, etc." (volume 24), and the "Report upon the Geology & Topography of the District on L. Superior Subdivided in 1846 by Hubbard & Ives" (loose material) have been published in
Report on the Geological and Mineralogical Survey of the Mineral Lands of the United States in the State of Michigan .., by Charles T. Jackson. Washington, D.C.: Printed for the House of Representatives, 1849. (31st Congress, 1st Session, House Executive Document 5, Part 3) [MHC call number EA/153/U58/M583]
The reports of Hubbard's surveys for the Michigan Geological Survey, based on his notes have been published in
Geological Reports of Douglass Houghton: First State Geologist of Michigan, 1837-1845. Lansing, Mich.: Michigan Historical Commission, 1928. [MHC call number EA/153/MG345/G345]
Hubbard's autobiography has been published as
Memorials of a Half-Century. New York: Putnam's, 1887. [MHC call number EA/60/H875/M533]
Other Bela Hubbard papers are found at the Burton Historical Collection, Detroit Public Library.
Subjects:
American Fur Company.; Barry County (Mich.); Berrien County (Mich.); Branch County (Mich.); Calhoun County (Mich.); Cass County (Mich.); Cliff Mine (Mich.); Clinton County (Mich.); Detroit Young Men's Society.; Douglas, Columbus C., 1812-1874.; Fishes--Michigan.; Fishing--Michigan.; Geology--Michigan.; Higgins, Sylvester W.; Hillsdale County (Mich.); Houghton, Douglass, 1809-1845.; Hubbard, Bela, 1814-1896.; Huron, Lake (Mich. and Ont.); Indians of North America--Michigan.; Ionia County (Mich.); Ives, William.; Kent County (Mich.); Keweenaw Peninsula (Mich.); Land use--Michigan.; Lapeer County (Mich.); Lenawee County (Mich.); Mackinac Island (Mich.); Macomb County (Mich.); Michigan, Lake.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Mines and mineral resources--Michigan.; Monroe County (Mich.); Oakland County (Mich.); Plymouth (Mich.); Porcupine Mountains (Mich.); Salt industry and trade--Michigan.; Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Notebooks
  - Vol. 1 September 13-October 13, 1837 (Box 1)
    [Field notes of geological excursion from Detroit to Tittabawassee and return by way of Lake Huron]
  - Vol. 2 May 19-July 24, 1838 (Box 1)
    [Field notes of peninsula coast survey from Detroit to Chicago]
  - Vol. 3 July 25-October 1, 1838 (Box 1)
    [Field notes, geological survey of Wayne County with part of coast survey, Chicago to Detroit]
  - Vol. 4 October 1-November 15, 1838 (Box 1)
    [Field notes, geological survey of Monroe County and part of Wayne]
  - Vol. 5 February 27-April 19, 1839 (Box 1)
    [Journey from Detroit via Canada to Utica, N.Y., and return via Pennsylvania]
  - Vol. 6 April 29, 1839-March 24, 1840 (Box 1)
    [Michigan]
  - Vol. 7 March 26-July 13, 1840 (Box 1)
    [Tour from Detroit via Ohio and Pennsylvania to Utica, N.Y. and return, and Journal on Lake Superior]
    (microfilm copy available)
  - Vol. 8 July 14-December 31, 1840 (Box 1)
    [Journal on Lake Superior, Detroit, and survey of Shiawassee, Clinton, Barry, Macomb, St. Clair, and Lapeer Counties]
  - Vol. 9 January 1841-September 1843 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 10 October 1843-February 1846 (Box 1)
    [Lake Superior, western counties, and others]
  - Vol. 11 March-September 1846 (Box 1)
    [Lake Superior region]
  - Vol. 12 September 1846-September 1851
    [Lake Superior and various Lower Peninsula Counties]
    (microfilm copy of portions available)
  - Vol. 13 October 1851-1856 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Vol. 14 October 1873-May 1878 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 15 November 1878-July 1880 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 16 July 1880-June 1882, October-December 1893 (Box 2)
  - Vol. 17 September-November 1884 (Box 2)
    (including weather notes, June 1882-September 1884 Detroit)
  - Vol. 18, Summary of weather 1835-1864 (Box 2)
  - Vol. 19, Day books 1843-1844 (Box 2)
  - Vol. 20, Weather book 1853 (Box 2)
  - Vol. 21, Geological field notes of Lake Superior coast survey and geological survey of Shiawassee, Clinton, Barry, Macomb, St. Clair, and Lapeer Counties May 21-September 22, 1840
  - Vol. 22, Meteorological register, May 26-July 31, Lake Superior; also draft maps of southern coast of Lake Superior
  - Vol. 23, Catalogue of the geological specimens, Hubbard & Ives survey 1846 (Box 2)
  - Vol. 24, Report on the geology &c. of district surveyed by Messrs. Higgins & Hubbard 1846 Lake Superior, with catalogue of minerals, sections, etc. (Box 2)
    [See also oversize unbound material]
- Reports, Miscellaneous Papers and Photographs
  - Evidences of the antiquity of the earth and its mutations 1843 (Box 2)
    [Read to the Detroit Young Men's Society]
  - Report upon the geology & topography of the district on L. Superior subdivided in 1846 by Hubbard & Ives (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 2)
    (include paper "The Aztecs - their civilization and its source" 1892
  - Photographs (Box 2)
    [Includes prints of sketches found in Notebooks: at this time only 1 print included]
- Oversize unbound material
  - Maps
    - [West and East Branches of Ontonagon River] 1846 (Folder 1)
      [Removed from Vol. 24]
    - Geological map, Presque Isle to Keweenaw Bay 1846 (Folder 1)
      [Removed from Report upon the geology & topography ... Hubbard & Ives]
    - [Part of Townships 51-52 North, Ranges 36-37 West] circa 1846 (Folder 1)
    - Section from SE cor. of T 51 N, R 37 W to mouth of Firesteel River circa 1846 (Folder 1)
Partial Notes on Contents of Notebooks
[Compiled by the initial cataloger of the collection in 1958, specifies where many of the topics indexed in the card catalog for this collection can be found in the series of notebooks]
June 22, 1838 Description of council held by Henry R. Schoolcraft with Chippewa on Mackinac Island
1840s Include descriptions of fishing at Sault Ste. Marie and other places
May 1840 Description of Sault Ste. Marie
July 1840 Description of the Chippewa of the Upper Peninsula
July 1840 Detailed description of copper veins near Copper Harbor
July 1840 Description of American Fur Co. post at La Pointe
July 1841 Description of Gypsum deposits near Ottawa Bay
July 1841 Account of a visit to the Saginaw salt well
1842-1845 Include information on land sales
Sept. 1845 Detailed description of copper veins near Copper Harbor
Oct. 16, 1845 Description of death of Douglass Houghton
1846 Include information on the mines of the Keweenaw Peninsula
1846 Description of iron mines
July 1846 Account of Cliff Mine operations
Aug. 1846 Include information on the Porcupine Mountains
1847 Include information on land sales
1850 Include information on land sales
Maps in the Collection
[Lake Huron shore-Port Hope to Sand Point]. 1837. 10x13 cm.
(Huron County)
(In Vol. 1)
[Lake Huron shore-Middle Island to near Mackinaw City, including Bois Blanc Island]. 1838. 1 map in 6 sections, each 16x10 cm.
(Alpena, Presque Isle, Cheboygan, and Mackinac Counties)
(In Vol. 2)
Map of Island of Mackinac. June, 1838. 16x10 cm.
(Mackinac County)
(In Vol. 2)
[Lake Huron and Lake Michigan shore-Mackinac Island to Cross Village]. 1838. 1 map in 2 sections, each 16x10 cm.
(Mackinac and Emmet Counties)
(In Vol. 2)
[Lake Michigan shore-Cross Village to about Torch Lake]. 1838. 1 map in 7 sections on 5 p., each 16x10 cm.
(Emmet, Charlevoix, and Antrim Counties)
(In Vol. 2)
[Lake Michigan shore-Old Mission Peninsula to Pyramid Point]. 1838. 1 map in 5 sections on 4 p., each 16x10 cm.
(Grand Traverse and Leelanau Counties)
(In Vol. 2)
[Lake Michigan shore-Pyramid Point to Portage Lake]. 1838. 1 map in 3 sections on 2 p., each 16x10 cm.
(Leelanau, Benzie, and Manistee Counties)
(In Vol. 2)
[Lake Michigan shore-Portage Lake to Pentwater]. 1838. 1 map in 2 sections each 16x10 cm.
(Manistee, Mason, and Oceana Counties)
(In Vol. 2)
[Lake Michigan shore-Pentwater to Black Creek]. 1838. 1 map in 3 sections each 16x10 cm.
(Oceana and Muskegon Counties)
(In Vol. 2)
[Huron River from Ypsilanti to mouth and Detroit River shore from Huron River to Gibraltar]. 1838. 1 map in 15 sections on 21 p., each 15x10 cm.
(Washtenaw, Wayne, and Monroe Counties)
(In Vol. 3)
Map of Gibraltar & vicinity, drawn by W. J. Alfris. 1838. 15x10 cm.
(Wayne County)
(In Vol. 3)
[Monroe and the mouth of the Raisin River]. 1838. 13x10 cm.
(Monroe County)
(In Vol. 4)
[Mouth of R. Au Vase, La Salle Township, Monroe County]. 1838. 8x10 cm.
(Monroe County)
(In Vol. 4)
[Routes from Detroit to Buffalo and Toronto. 1839 ?]. (25x28 cm.)
(Ontario)
(In Vol. 5)
Draft of southern coast of Lake Superior. 1840. 23 p.; 16x10 cm.
(Chippewa, Luce, Alger, Marquette, Baraga, Houghton, Keweenaw, Ontonagon, Gogebic Counties, and Wisconsin)
(In Vol. 2)
2
Plan of old Ft. St. Joseph. 1840. 10x17 cm.
(Ontario)
(In Vol. 2)
1
View of the rock succession from Chocolate R. to the appearance of granite W. of Presque Isle. 1840. 1 map in 2 parts, 9x17 and 20x10 cm.
(Marquette County)
(In Vol. 2)
1
Map of the country adjoining R. au Gres. 1840. 17x10 cm.
(Keweenaw County)
(In Vol. 2)
1
[Lake Superior coast from Bete Grise Bay to La Pointe, Wisconsin]. 1840. 1 map in 14 sections on 13 p., each 17x10 cm.
(Keweenaw, Houghton, Ontonagon, Gogebic Counties, and Wisconsin)
(In Vol. 2)
1
[Lake Huron shore-Les Cheneaux Islands]. 1840. 10x16 cm.
(Mackinac County)
(In Vol. 7)
[Part of Township 7 North, Range 7 West]. 1840. 12x8 cm.
(Ionia County)
(In Vol. 8)
[Part of Township 6 North, Range 10 West]. 1840 12x10 cm.
(Kent County)
(In Vol. 8)
[Part of Township 7 North, Range 10 West]. 1840. 15x10 cm.
(Kent County)
(In Vol. 8)
[Part of Township 4 North, Range 10 West]. 1840. 10x17 cm.
(Barry County)
(In Vol. 8)
[Part of Township 3 North, Range 10 West]. 1840. 15x10 cm.
(Barry County)
(In Vol. 8)
[Geology from Quebec City west to Lake Michigan and from New York City north to James Bay]. 1846. 20x17 cm.
(Ontario)
(Journal, March 3-June 16, 1846 in Vol. 11)
Map of Riv. Ste. Marie. 1846. 13x10 cm.
(Mackinac and Chippewa Counties, and Ontario)
(Journal, June 17-27, 1846 in Vol. 11)
[Map of the area around the Cliff Mine]. 1846. 10x10 cm.
(Keweenaw County)
(Journal, June 27-July 3, 1846 in Vol. 11)
Ground plan of vein in conglomerate coast, from Giraffe vein, easterly 30 rods ... (Keweenaw Pt.). 1846. 9x16 cm.
(Keweenaw County)
(Journal June 27-July 3, 1846 in Vol. 11)
[Map of Lac La Belle Location]. 1846. 6x5 cm.
(Keweenaw County)
(Journal, July 3-8, 1846 in Vol. 11)
Garlic River Point. 1846. 7x8 cm.
(Marquette County)
(Journal, July 9-16, 1846 in Vol. 11)
North end of Granite Point. 1846. 5x7 cm.
(Marquette County)
(Journal, July 9-16, 1846 in Vol. 11)
[Carp River, Ontonagon County]. 1846. 9x5 cm.
(Ontonagon County)
(Journal, August 5-11, 1846 in Vol. 11)
Union Compy. veins, etc. 1846. 5x9 cm.
(Ontonagon County)
(Journal, August 5-11, 1846 in Vol. 11)
[Cushman's Location, Ontonagon River]. 1846. 4x8 cm.
(Ontonagon County)
(Journal, August 12-20, 1846 in Vol. 11)
Geological map, Presque Isle to Keweenaw Bay. Accompanying report Hubbard & Ives' survey. 1846. 35x53 cm.
(Marquette and Baraga Counties)
(Outsize material)
[West and East Branches of Ontonagon River]. 1846. 16x31 cm.
(Ontonagon County)
(Outsize material)
[Part of Townships 51-52 North, Ranges 36-37 West. 1846 ?] 17x50 cm.
(Houghton and Ontonagon Counties)
(Outsize material)
Madison [Wisconsin, showing Indian mounds]. 1874. 2 maps; 15x10 cm. and 12x10 cm.
(Wisconsin)
(Journal, September 10-22, 1874 in Vol. 14)
Maps cataloged separately
[Maps of townships in Washtenaw County]. [ca. 1840]
(Washtenaw County)
(Originals in the Burton Historical Collection, Detroit Public Library. Shows roads, railroads, buildings, sawmills, vegetation, natural features.)
(Cataloged separately as M 4113 .W2 1840 H8)